Louise Bates Ames Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Louise Bates Ames Papers 1915-1989 1950-1975
MSS10868
Ames, Louise Bates
14,000 items
52 containers
20.4 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Child psychologist and educator. Personal and professional correspondence, diaries, manuscripts of articles and books, lectures and speeches, subject files, bibliography, photographs, newspaper clippings, biographical material on the Bates family, and other papers chiefly documenting Ames's career as a child psychologist.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Ames, Louise Bates.; Bates family.; Bates, Annie E.--Correspondence.; Chase, Joan Ames--Correspondence.; Culbertson, James T. (James Thomas), 1911- --Correspondence.; Dodson, Fitzhugh, 1923- --Correspondence.; Elicker, Paul H.--Correspondence.; Gesell, Arnold, 1880-1961--Correspondence.; Gesell, Gerhard Alden, 1910-1993--Correspondence.; Ilg, Frances L. (Frances Lillian), 1902-1981. Frances Lillian Ilg papers.; Johnson, Eric W.--Correspondence.; Lye, Len, 1901-1980--Correspondence.; Mead, Margaret, 1901-1978--Correspondence.; Moynihan, Daniel P. (Daniel Patrick), 1927-2003--Correspondence.; Métraux, Guy S. (Guy Serge)--Correspondence.; Métraux, Ruth W.--Correspondence.; Packard, Vance, 1914-1996--Correspondence.; Pitcher, Evelyn Goodenough--Correspondence.; Slosson, Richard L.--Correspondence.; Spock, Benjamin, 1903-1998--Correspondence.; Zingg, Robert M. (Robert Mowry), 1900-1957. Robert M. Zingg research files.
Organizations
Gesell Institute of Child Development.; United States. Department of Health, Education, and Welfare.; White House Conference on Children (1970: Washington, D.C.); Yale University. Child Study Center.; Yale University. Clinic of Child Development.
Subjects
Advice columns.; Child development.; Child psychology.; Feral children.; Mental health facilities--Connecticut--New Haven.
Occupations
Child psychologists.; Educators.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Louise Bates Ames, child psychologist and educator, were given to the Library of Congress by Ames and Frances Lillian Ilg in 1964. Ames made subsequent gifts between 1966 and 1996.
Transfers
Items have been transferred from the Manuscript Division to other custodial divisions of the Library. Some photographs were transferred to the Prints and Photographs Division. Sound and video recordings were transferred to the Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division. All transfers are identified in these divisions as part of the Louise Bates Ames Papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Louise Bates Ames are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1908, Oct. 29 Born, Portland, Maine
1930 Married Smith Whittier Ames (divorced 1937) B.A., University of Maine, Orono, Maine
1933 M.A., University of Maine, Orono, Maine
1933 1936 Research secretary and personal assistant to Arnold Gesell, Clinic of Child Development, Yale University, New Haven, Conn.
1936 Ph.D., Yale University, New Haven, Conn.
1938 Produced first film, "How Behavior Grows: The Sequential Patterning of Prone Progression"
1940 1944 Instructor, Clinic of Child Development, Yale University, New Haven, Conn.
1943 Published with Arnold Gesell, Frances Lillian Ilg, and Janet Learned Infant and Child in the Culture of Today: The Guidance of Development in Home and Nursery School (New York: Harper & Brothers. 405 pp.)
1944 1950 Assistant Professor and curator of the Yale Films of Child Development, Clinic of Child Development, Yale University, New Haven, Conn.
1946 Published with Arnold Gesell, Frances Lillian Ilg, and Glenna E. Bullis Child from Five to Ten (New York: Harper & Brothers. 458 pp.)
1950 Founded with Frances Lillian Ilg the Gesell Institute of Child Development, New Haven, Conn.
1950 1968 Director of research and secretary-treasurer, Gesell Institute of Child Development, New Haven, Conn.
1951 1973 Coauthor of syndicated newspaper column Child Behavior (after 1962 called Parents Ask)
1952 1955 Weekly television series, Child Behavior
1960 1961 Weekly television series, The Gesell Institute Reports: Your Child and You
1965 Published with Frances Lillian Ilg School Readiness: Behavior Tests Used at the Gesell Institute (New York: Harper & Row. 396 pp.)
1968 Associate director and chief psychologist, Gesell Institute of Child Development, New Haven, Conn.
1970 Published Child Care and Development (Philadelphia: Lippincott Co. 426 pp.)
1971 1977 Codirector, Gesell Institute of Child Development, New Haven, Conn.
1973 Published Rorschach Responses in Old Age (New York: Brunner/Mazel. 219 pp.)
1974 Published with Joan Ames Chase Don't Push Your Pre-schooler (New York: Harper & Row. 212 pp.)
1976 Published series on child development with Frances Lillian Ilg, beginning with Your Two-Year-Old: Terrible or Tender (New York: Delacorte Press. 149 pp.)
1978 Gesell Institute of Child Development, New Haven, Conn., renamed Gesell Institute of Human Development, New Haven, Conn.
1989 Published Arnold Gesell: Themes of His Work (New York: Human Sciences Press. 334 pp.)
1990 Reaffiliation of the Gesell Institute of Human Development with Yale University, New Haven, Conn.
1991 Lecturer, Child Study Center, Yale University, New Haven, Conn.
1996, Oct. 31 Died, Cincinnati, Ohio
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Louise Bates Ames (1908-1996) span the period 1915-1989, with the bulk of the material dating from 1950 to 1975. The collection consists primarily of correspondence and manuscript material relating to Ames's career as a child psychologist, cofounder and codirector of the Gesell Institute of Child Development, and author of numerous books and articles on child behavior and child development. Included in the collection are family correspondence, correspondence with friends and professional associates, a sampling of letters related to the syndicated newspaper column Parents Ask, and manuscripts and related correspondence for several of Ames's books and articles. The collection is organized in six original series and five additions. The original series include Family Correspondence, Special Correspondence, General Correspondence, "Parents Ask" Newspaper Column, Writings, and Miscellany. The additions are dated according to the year of their arrangement and contain material organized in the same schema as the original part.
Ames's career as a child psychologist began in 1933 when she joined the staff of the Yale Clinic of Child Development as research secretary and personal assistant to the director, Arnold Gesell, with whom she worked until 1948. She received her doctorate in psychology from Yale University in 1936; was curator of the Yale Films of Child Development, 1944-1950; and participated in the development of articles, books, and research projects in the field of child psychology. Material in the collection which relates to this period may be found in the following series: Family Correspondence, especially letters to Annie E. Bates; Special Correspondence, in particular correspondence with James T. Culbertson, Paul H. Elicker, Guy S. Métraux, and Ruth W. Métraux; Writings File, "Guide to the Yale Films of Child Development" by Louise Bates Ames; and Miscellany containing a diary, 1928-1937, and annual reports, 1939-1949.
After Gesell's retirement, the clinic separated from Yale University, and in 1950, Ames and her associate, Frances Lillian Ilg, founded the Gesell Institute of Child Development. The institute's name changed to the Gesell Institute of Human Development in 1978. The Gesell Institute is a private, nonprofit corporation for clinical research in the field of child psychology. Ames was Director of Research at the Institute until 1968 when she became codirector. In conjunction with her study of children's behavior at successive age intervals, Ames became one of the pioneers of rorschach psychological testing. References to this and other aspects of her work may be found in the Family and Special Correspondence series, in particular, the letters of Annie E. Bates, Joan Ames Chase, Len Lye, Guy S. Métraux, Ruth W. Métraux, and Evelyn Goodenough Pitcher. More detailed information about rorschach testing may be found in Ames's numerous books and articles, bibliographies of which are in Miscellany.
As the work of the Gesell Institute became increasingly recognized, requests for lectures, television appearances, and articles began to increase as well. This aspect of Ames's career is well documented in her papers. In the Special Correspondence series are files relating to her two television series, Child Behavior and The Gesell Institute Reports: Your Child and You. In 1951, Ames and Ilg began their syndicated newspaper column, Child Behavior, which in 1962 became known as Parents Ask. A sampling of unedited letters from the column for the period 1954-1964 is included in the collection as well as two sets of the edited and published columns covering the years 1967-1968. Research files of Robert M. Zingg on "wolf-children" are included in the 1977 addition.
Ames corresponded with numerous friends, colleagues, and associates, many of whom were prominent in their fields. Among those whose letters are contained in the Special Correspondence series are Fitzhugh Dodson, Arnold Gesell, Gerhard Alden Gesell, Len Lye, Margaret Mead, Daniel P. Moynihan, Vance Packard, and Benjamin Spock. Also in the Special Correspondence series are files concerning Ames's work with the Department of Health, Education, and Welfare and the White House Conference on Children and Youth in 1970-1971.
Among the papers are drafts, readers' proofs, and publishers' correspondence for seven of Ames's books: Child Care and Development (1970), Don't Push Your Pre-Schooler (1973), Infant and Child in the Culture of Today (revised edition 1974), Is Your Child in the Wrong Grade? (1967), Mosaic Patterns of American Children (1962), School Readiness (1964), and Stop School Failure (1972). In addition, there is correspondence relating to several book reviews and a draft essay for inclusion in the book Summerhill: For and Against, published in 1970 by Hart Publishing Company.
Arrangement of the Papers
The collection is arranged in eleven series:
Family Correspondence, 1915-1975
Special Correspondence, 1935-1975
General Correspondence, 1941-1974
"Parents Ask" Newspaper Column, 1954-1968
Writings, 1947-1974
Miscellany, 1922-1975
1977 Addition, 1937-1977
1984 Addition, 1940-1983
1987 Addition,1941-1986
1988 Addition, 1941-1988
1996 Addition, circa 1945-1996
Container List
- Family Correspondence, 1915-1975 (Box 1-2)
  Correspondence to and from family members, in particular Ames's mother, Annie E. Bates, and daughter, Joan Ames Chase. Included are Bates's rorschach responses that became the basis for Ames's Rorschach Responses in Old Age.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - Ames, Smith Whittier (former husband), 1946-1975 (Box 1)
  - Bates, Annie E. (mother)
    - Correspondence, 1915-1916, 1932-1944, 1954-1963, (13 folders)
    - Rorschach responses, 1948-1963 (Box 2)
  - Bates, Kay (sister-in-law), 1957
  - Chase, Joan Ames (daughter), 1953-1970, (3 folders)
  - Spaulding, Ella (aunt), 1957-1960
- Special Correspondence, 1935-1975 (Box 2-7)
  Correspondence to and from friends, colleagues, child psychologists, authors, newspaper editors, television producers, and government officials.
  - Boppert, Walter T., 1971-1975, (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Collier, Herbert L., 1971-1973
  - Culbertson, James T.
    - 1937-1940, (4 folders)
    - 1941-1946, undated, (4 folders) (Box 3)
  - Dodd, Thomas J., 1961-1964
  - Dodson, Fitzhugh, 1969-1973
  - Elicker, Paul H., 1943-1946
  - Gesell, Arnold, 1935-1964
  - Gesell, Gerhard Alden, 1964
  - Goodenough, Evelyn See Container 7, Pitcher, Evelyn Goodenough
  - Hall Newspaper Syndicate
    - 1951-1958, (4 folders)
    - 1959-1969, (5 folders) (Box 4)
  - Hart Publishing Co., regarding Summerhill: For and Against, 1969-1970
  - Health, Education, and Welfare, Department of, 1962-1968
  - Ilg, Frances Lillian, 1945-1961
  - Johnson, Eric W., 1968-1974
  - Larson, R. K. T. (Kit), 1960-1971
  - Lye, Len, 1945-1967, undated, (6 folders) (Box 5)
  - Mead, Margaret, 1952-1954 (Box 6)
  - Métraux, Ruth W. and Guy S., 1942-1974, (7 folders)
  - Moore, Raymond S., 1972-1974
  - Moynihan, Daniel P., 1969-1970
  - Packard, Vance, 1965-1969
  - Perris, Donald L., 1960-1969
  - Pitcher, Evelyn Goodenough, 1959-1964 (Box 7)
  - Sands, Alan, 1955-1958
  - See, Harold P., 1961-1964
  - Silberberg, Norman E., 1969-1974
  - Silverthorne, Henry, 1954-1963
  - Slosson, Richard L., 1961-1967
  - Spock, Benjamin, 1961-1962
  - Taylor, John I., 1952-1957, (3 folders)
  - U.S. Public Health Service, 1948
  - White House Conference on Children and Youth, 1970-1971, (2 folders)
- General Correspondence, 1941-1974 (Box 8-9)
  Letters to and from the general public regarding the column Parents Ask and from psychologists and students concerning research projects and books. Some business correspondence is also included.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1941-1963, (11 folders) (Box 8)
  - 1964-1974, undated, (11 folders) (Box 9)
- "Parents Ask" Newspaper Column, 1954-1968 (Box 10-16)
  A sampling of letters to and from readers of the syndicated column Parents Ask (called Child Behavior until 1962) and a set of columns for the years 1967-1968.
  Letters are arranged chronologically by year and thereunder alphabetically by name of correspondent. Columns are arranged chronologically.
  - Letters from readers (Box 10)
    - 1954-1956, (6 folders)
    - 1957
      - A-L
      - M-W (Box 11)
    - 1958-1960, (4 folders)
    - 1961
      - A-C
      - D-Y and anonymous, (4 folders) (Box 12)
    - 1962
      - A-L, (2 folders)
      - L-Y and anonymous, (2 folders) (Box 13)
    - 1963
      - Ac-Mc, (3 folders)
      - Me-Wo and anonymous, (2 folders) (Box 14)
    - 1964, (3 folders)
  - Column (Box 15)
    - 1967, (6 folders)
    - 1968, (6 folders) (Box 16)
- Writings, 1947-1974 (Box 17-26)
  Drafts, proofs, and publishers' correspondence relating to Ames's books and a small collection of articles written by others. Books are arranged alphabetically by title.
  Articles are arranged alphabetically by name of author.
  - Child Care and Development (Box 17)
    - Correspondence
      - Rand McNally and Co., 1966-1970, (2 folders)
      - J. B. Lippincott Co., 1968-1970
    - Preliminary chapter outlines, 1966-1969
    - Draft, (9 folders)
    - Draft, (17 folders) (Box 18)
  - Don't Push Your Pre-Schooler (Box 19)
    - Typescript, (5 folders)
    - Carbon copy, (4 folders)
    - Reader's proof, (3 folders)
  - Infant and Child in the Culture of Today, typescript for revised edition, 1974, (8 folders) (Box 20)
  - Is Your Child in the Wrong Grade? (Box 21)
    - Correspondence, Harper & Row, Publishers, 1966
    - Outlines
    - First draft, (3 folders)
    - Printer's copy, (3 folders)
  - Mosaic Patterns of American Children
    - Correspondence, 1950-1964, (3 folders)
    - Typescript, (1 folder)
    - Typescript, (7 folders) (Box 22)
  - School Readiness
    - Typescript, (3 folders)
    - Typescript, (5 folders) (Box 23)
    - Carbon copy, (4 folders)
    - Carbon copy, (2 folders) (Box 24)
  - Stop School Failure
    - Correspondence
      - Harper & Row, Publishers, 1970-1972
      - J. B. Lippincott Co., 1969-1970
    - Manuscript No. 1, (5 folders)
    - Manuscript No. 2, (4 folders) (Box 25)
    - Reader's proof, (2 folders)
  - Guide to the Yale Films of Child Development, 1947
  - Blanchard, Irene
    - "A Study of Articulation Tests Suitable for Use with Institutionalized Mentally Retarded Children"
    - "Diagnostic Patterns of Articulation" (Box 26)
  - Cohen, Wilbur J., and Wallace K. Babington, "Implications of 1965 Federal Legislation for Mental Retardation"
  - Crouch, Zilpha B., "Various Aspects of Teaching the Mentally Retarded Child with Emphasis on Information Value to the Speech Therapist"
  - Waldon, Edgar F.
    - "The Baby Cry Test: A Meaningful Acoustic Signal for Testing Subnormal Children"
    - "The Baby Cry Test (BCT): A New Audiometric Technique for Testing Very Young Children"
    - "Testing Hearing of Subnormal Children"
    - "Testing of Infants: Implications for Audio-Reflexometry"
- Miscellany, 1922-1975 (Box 26)
  Annual reports, awards, a diary, appointment calendars, lists of lectures, newspaper clippings, and receipts.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  - Annual reports, 1939-1949 (Box 26)
  - Appointment calendars, 1953, 1960
  - Awards, bibliographies, and biographies, 1957-1974
  - Bibliography, 1933-1965
  - Certification, American Psychological Association, 1943
  - Diary, 1928-1937
  - Lists of lectures, 1952-1975
  - Journal of lectures, 1966-1967
  - News clippings, 1964-1965, undated
  - Pamphlets, 1951-1952, undated
  - Poem, 1922
  - Receipts, 1957-1963
- 1977 Addition, 1937-1977 (Box 27-31)
  Correspondence with family, friends, colleagues, publishers, and the public; a subject file concerning the television program Playmates/Schoolmates; a writings file largely concerning Don't Push Your Pre-schooler; and miscellany. Also included are research files of Robert M. Zingg on "wolf-children."
  Arranged by family correspondence, special correspondence, general correspondence, subject file, writings file, miscellany, and the Robert M. Zingg Papers and alphabetically thereunder by name of person, subject, or type of material.
  - Family correspondence, Ames, Smith Whittier (former husband), 1937-1977 (Box 27)
  - Special correspondence
    - Arthur, Phyllis-Marie, 1945-1977
    - Dickinson, Alice, 1974-1977
    - Hobson, Dick, 1948-1957
    - Lowenfeld, Margaret, 1966-1970
    - Lye, Ann and Len, 1962-1975
    - Métraux, Ruth W., 1966-1967
    - Ostler, Renée, 1967
    - Perris, Donald L. and Barbara, 1964-1977
    - Rodell, Fred and Janet, 1953-1976
    - Von Hilsheimer, George, 1967-1977
    - Wunderlich, Ray C., 1965-1975
  - General correspondence (Box 28)
    - "A-Z" miscellaneous, 1968-1977, (4 folders)
    - Correspondence with publisher regarding books reviewed by Ames, 1962-1974
    - Letters from fans, 1952-1977
  - Subject file, Playmates/Schoolmates, television program, 1975-1976
  - Writings file (Box 29)
    - Don't Push Your Pre-schooler, by Ames and Joan Ames Chase, correspondence, 1972-1975
    - Robert L. Lewin/Mill Pond Press project, 1972-1977
  - Miscellany
    - Letter from Arnold Gesell to Joan Ames Chase, 1952
    - Schedule of lecture and television appearances, 1976-1977
  - Robert M. Zingg papers
    - Correspondence, 1937-1945
      - "A-Z" miscellaneous, (2 folders)
      - Allen & Unwin Ltd.
      - American Journal of Psychology
      - The American Weekly
      - Davis, Kingsley
      - Dennis, Wayne
      - Eckels, Richard P.
      - Gates, R. R.
      - Gesell, Arnold
      - Harper & Brothers (Box 30)
      - Hollander, Sidney
      - Houghton Mifflin Co.
      - Hutton, J. H.
      - Life magazine
      - Literary Services-Mondiale Ltd.
      - Maxfield, Francis
      - Pakenham, Walsh H.
      - Redfield, Robert
      - Singh, J. A. L.
      - Singh, Mrs. J. A. L.
      - Vanguard Press
      - Wirth, Louis
    - Subject file
      - "Baboon" boy of South Africa
      - The "Tarzancito" case
    - Writings file (Box 31)
      - Gesell, Arnold, chronology of the "wolf-children"
      - Miscellany
      - Singh, J. A. L., "Diary of the wolf-children of Midnapore"
      - Zingg, Robert M.
    - Miscellany
      - Newspaper clippings regarding "wolf-children"
      - Photographs of "wolf-children"
      - Printed matter and bibliographic notes
- 1984 Addition, 1940-1983 (Box 32-40)
  Correspondence with friends, colleagues, publishers, and the public; diary excerpts, photographs, biographical material, and printed matter; condolence letters on the death of Ames's daughter; correspondence of Frances Lillian Ilg; research, lectures, and writings by Ames and Arnold Gesell; and files concerning the Gesell Institute of Child Development, White House Conference on Children and Youth, and Ames's radio and television programs.
  Arranged by special correspondence, condolences, general correspondence, diary excerpts, subject file, speeches and lectures file, writings file, and miscellany and alphabetically thereunder by name of person, subject, title, or type of material.
  - Special correspondence (Box 32)
    - Balkany, Robert de, 1951-1968
    - Brilliant, Ira, 1959-1961
    - Bull, Nina, 1942-1947
    - Cox, Don and Jo, 1974-1977
    - Culbertson, James T., 1941-1976
    - Curnow, Wystan, regarding Len Lye, 1982
    - Ertel, Paul Y. and Inta, 1974-1978
    - Gesell, Arnold, 1955-1960
    - Homberger, Gin and Freddy, 1943-1981, (3 folders)
    - Ilg, Frances Lillian
      - With Ames, 1965-1978
      - With Margaret Mead, 1946-1966
    - Métraux, Ruth W. and Guy S., 1943-1982, (3 folders) (Box 33)
    - Scharbert, Beatrice, 1970-1976
    - Sheldon, William H., 1950-1978
    - Silverthorne, Pen, 1958-1964
    - Taylor, John I., circa 1951-1975
    - Webb, Rachel, 1973-1979
    - Wunderlich, Ray C., 1964-1965
  - Condolences on death of daughter, son-in-law, and grandson, 1974, (2 folders) (Box 34)
  - General correspondence
    - Of Ames, 1944-1983, undated, (6 folders)
    - Of Frances Lillian Ilg
      - 1944-1951, (2 folders)
      - 1952-1970, (9 folders) (Box 35)
      - Undated and Ilg miscellany
  - Diary excerpts, 1945-1982 (Box 36)
  - Subject file
    - Adolescent rorschach responses, 1950-1959
    - Books received for review, 1951-1978
    - Child Care and Development, 1976-1981
    - Child from Five to Ten, by Frances Lillian Ilg, undated
    - Controversies with Yale University, New Haven, Conn.; Bernard B. Shapiro; Life magazine; and others, 1957-1980
    - First Five Years of Life, 1978-1979
    - Gesell, Arnold
      - Genius, Giftedness and Intelligence, undated
      - Sigma Xi lectures, 1947-1949 See also Container 38, Lectures by Arnold Gesell
      - Translations of books by, 1956-1958
    - Harper & Row, Publishers, 1967-1981, (2 folders) (Box 37)
    - Infant and Child, 1972-1973
    - Journal of Learning Disabilities, 1967-1977
    - Marks, Philip A., 1974-1977
    - Playmates/Schoolmates television program, 1975-1976
    - Radio series, 1968
    - School Readiness, 1956-1966
    - Screen gems, 1970-1972
    - Society of Protective Techniques, 1968-1972
    - White House Conference on Children and Youth, 1970
  - Speeches and lectures file (Box 38)
    - Lectures by Arnold Gesell, 1948-1949 See also Container 36, Sigma Xi lectures
    - Lists of Ames's lectures, 1940-1983
  - Writings file
    - Articles by Ames regarding her books
    - Book reviews, 1970-1975
    - Development of Motor Coordination, from Birth to Two Years, typescript, (2 folders)
    - Infant and Child in the Culture of Today (Box 39)
    - Your Two Year Old
    - Your Three Year Old
    - Your Four Year Old
    - Your Six Year Old
  - Miscellany
    - Photographs
      - Album
      - Miscellany
    - General (Box 40)
    - Printed matter
      - Biographical file
      - Clippings and general printed matter
      - Infancy and Human Growth, by Arnold Gesell
- 1987 Addition, 1941-1986 (Box 41-42)
  Correspondence with family, friends, colleagues, publishers, and the public; dream diaries; articles; lecture schedule; and biographical and genealogical information.